<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The vveapon-salves maladie: or, A declaration of its insufficiencie to performe what is attributed to it Wherein also is described, 1. The severall wayes of making the weapon-salve. 2. The manner of vsing it. 3. Reasons of confirmation to justifie it. 4. Arguments of confutation to overthrow it. By the learned and judicious physitian Daniell Sennertus, Doctor and publique professor at Wittenberg. Translated out of his 5th. booke, part. 4. chap. 10. Practicæ medicinæ.</title>
            <title>Practicae medicinae. Booke 5. Part 4. English</title>
            <author>Sennerts, Daniel, 1572-1637.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1637</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 52 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11920</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22232</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105181</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840910</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840910</idno>
            <idno type="VID">5454</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11920)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5454)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 937:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The vveapon-salves maladie: or, A declaration of its insufficiencie to performe what is attributed to it Wherein also is described, 1. The severall wayes of making the weapon-salve. 2. The manner of vsing it. 3. Reasons of confirmation to justifie it. 4. Arguments of confutation to overthrow it. By the learned and judicious physitian Daniell Sennertus, Doctor and publique professor at Wittenberg. Translated out of his 5th. booke, part. 4. chap. 10. Practicæ medicinæ.</title>
                  <title>Practicae medicinae. Booke 5. Part 4. English</title>
                  <author>Sennerts, Daniel, 1572-1637.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 29, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by B. Alsop and T. Fawcet] for Iohn Clark, and are to be sold at his shop vnder St. Peters Church in Cornhill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1637.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printers' names from STC.</note>
                  <note>An English translation of the fifth book of Daniel Sennerts' Practicæ medicinæ.</note>
                  <note>Title page has left brace brackets from "The severall .. overthrow it".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Harvard University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Medicine --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:5454:1"/>
            <p>THE WEAPON-SALVES MALADIE: <hi>OR,</hi> A DECLARATION OF ITS INSVFFICIENCIE TO performe what is attributed to it. Wherein alſo is deſcribed,
<list>
                  <item>1 <hi>The ſeverall wayes of making the Weapon-Salve.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2 <hi>The manner of vſing it.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3 <hi>Reaſons of Confirmation to juſtifie it.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4 <hi>Arguments of Confutation to overthrow it.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>BY The learned and judicious Phyſitian DANIELL SENNERTUS, Doctor and publique Profeſſor at WITTENBERG. Tranſlated out of his 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. Booke, <hi>Part.</hi> 4. <hi>Chap.</hi> 10. <hi>Practicae Medicinae.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for IOHN CLARK, and are to be ſold at his Shop <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:5454:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5454:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>HRISTIAN READER,</hi> This Argument of the <hi>Weapon-Salve,</hi> is a thing often talked of in private Meetings a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Friends, and not ſeldome diſputed of by Learned men in their publike Writings. Nor can any man with rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon blame them for ſifting out the Truth; eſpecially, in a point that involveth a caſe of <hi>Conſcience</hi> in it, the miſtaking whereof, might breed an offence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt GOD and his Sacred truth. But yet they are blame worthy, who in ſearching for the Truth doe fly upon their Adverſarie with uncivill lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage. In which kinde, I muſt needes confeſſe Mr. <hi>FOSTER</hi> hath exceeded the bounds of Chriſtian cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie. Hee hath in mine opinion the Truth on his ſide, and hath cleared it well: but yet hee ſhould have remembred the Apoſtles rule, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Epheſ. <hi>4.15. That wee ſpeake the truth,</hi> or (as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers tranſlate it) <hi>follow the truth in love;</hi> Not forgetting, that even the Heathen could ſay,<note n="(a)" place="margin">Tuſcul. Q. lib. <hi>2.</hi> fol. <hi>176.</hi> Aldin, edit.</note> 
               <hi>Et
<pb facs="tcp:5454:3"/> refellere ſine pertinaria, &amp; refelli ſine iracundia parati ſumus.</hi> And againe,<note n="(b)" place="margin">De finib. lib. <hi>2</hi> fol. <hi>81.</hi> pag <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Sit iſta in Graeco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum levitate perverſitas, qui malidictis inſectan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur eos, à quibus de veritate diſſentiunt:</hi> That is, <hi>Let the light-brain'd Grecians purſue them with reproaches, who diſſent from them in opinion: wee are ready both to refute without pertinacie, and to bee refuted without anger.</hi> Theſe rules I wiſh had beene obſerved in that Diſputation; eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally conſidering that the Adverſary whom hee oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, is a learned Doctor, well eſteemed at home for his practicall skill in Phyſick, and much<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>. Iacob. Boiſſard. Bibli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oth. claroru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rorum, part. <hi>2.</hi> effigie <hi>60.</hi> pag. <hi>198.</hi>
               </note> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured abroad for his learned Bookes in Print.</p>
            <p>Now this little Treatiſe, ſent abroad in our <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> tongue, is the worke of a man not onely famous for his Learning, but one that had no intereſt in theſe perſonall quarrels. And therefore, I hope the learned Doctor will with his good leave permit vs to publiſh this ſmall Treatiſe in our Mother tongue, for the direction of ſuch, as ſeeke ſatisfaction in this queſtionable Point. And that is all, that eyther the Tranſlator or Publiſher doe ſeeke after in this Worke. GOD grant vs peace and truth in <hi>CHRIST</hi> our Lord, Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <p>PErlegi librum hunc cui Titulus eſt <hi>[The Weapon-Salves ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladie,]</hi> nec in eo quicquam repetio quò minùs cum utilitate publicâ imprimatur.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Ex aedib: Londin:
<date>
                     <hi>Ian.</hi> 20. 1636.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>SA: BAKER.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:5454:3"/>
            <head>THE VVEAPON-SALVES MALADIE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat which hath beene ſaid in the precedent Chapter, concerning the opinion of <hi>Caeſar Magatus,</hi> and <hi>Ludovicus Septalius,</hi> of the Cure of Wounds, puts mee in minde of that Oyntment which is commonly called the <hi>Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon-Salve.</hi> For as the greene Wounds of the fleſh, as is ſaid in the precedent Chapter, are hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led without much adoe, and without the fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent opening of the Wound, or applying many Salves, onely by the benefit of meere Nature; juſt ſo thoſe Wounds, which are thought to bee Cured by the <hi>Weapon-ſalve,</hi> I think to bee cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the help of Nature onely.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:5454:4"/>
            <p>But ſince ſome others determine the contrary, let us in this place conſider what is to be thought of this <hi>Weapon-Salve.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And firſt of all, wee will lay downe the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall deſcriptions of this <hi>Weapon-Salve,</hi> and then the uſe of it; and then the things they uſe to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce in its defence.</p>
            <p>Moſt men attribute this Vnguent to <hi>Paracelſus,</hi> or affirme it certainly to be divulged by him.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celſus.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Paracelſus</hi> himſelf, <hi>Archidox: Magicae, lib.</hi> 1. giveth this deſcription of it;
<list>
                  <item>Take <hi>Scull-Moſſe,</hi> two Ounces,</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mummy,</hi> halfe an ounce,</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mans fat,</hi> two ounces,</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mans blood,</hi> halfe an ounce,</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Linſeed Oyle,</hi> two Drams,</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Oyle of Roſes,</hi> and</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Bole Armoniack,</hi> of each one ounce.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Mixe them together and make an Oyntment: Into the which hee puts a Stick, dipp'd in the Blood of the wounded perſon, and dryed, and bindeth up the wound with a rowler dipt every day in the hot Vrine of the wounded perſon. For the annointing of the Weapon hee addes moreover;
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Honey,</hi> one ounce,</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Bulls fat,</hi> one dram.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Porta</hi> his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of it, &amp;c.</note>
               <hi>Iohannes Baptiſta Porta, Mag: Nat: lib.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 12. Writes thus of it; The <hi>Weapon-Salve</hi> which was long ſince given by <hi>Paracelſus</hi> to <hi>Maximi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lianus Caeſar,</hi> and by him uſed, and made very chary of ſo long as hee lived, was communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:5454:4"/> to mee, by a Nobleman of his Court. If the Weapon which hath wounded any one ſhall bee brought, or a Stick dipp'd in the ſame Blood; the affected perſon ſhall be Cured, although he be diſtant farre away:</p>
            <p>
               <list>
                  <item>Take <hi>Moſſe</hi> or <hi>Scurffe</hi> (that groweth thick, on a Mans ſcull left to the open ayre,) and </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mans fat,</hi> of each two Ounces,</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mummy,</hi> and</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mans blood,</hi> of each halfe an ounce,</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Linſeed Oyle,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Turpentine,</hi> and</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Bole Armoniack,</hi> of each one ounce.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Let all theſe things bee brayed together in a Morter, and kept in a long and narrow pot. Dip the Weapon into the Vnguent, and there let it lye: Let the perſon hurt, in the morning cleanſe his Wound with his owne water; and ſo bind it up, without any thing elſe put to it, and the wounded perſon ſhall bee cured without any paine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Crollius</hi> himſelf alſo,<note place="margin">The deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Crol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius.</hi>
               </note> attributeth it to <hi>Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celſus,</hi> and calleth it the Sympatheticall or Starry oyntment of <hi>Paracelſus,</hi> and deſcribeth it thus:</p>
            <p>Take <hi>Wild-Boares greaſe,</hi> and <hi>Beares greaſe,</hi> of each foure ounces.</p>
            <p>The elder the Beaſts are, the better is their Fat, and firſt let the Fat of eyther beaſt, boyle ſoftly in Red Wine, over a gentle fire, for the ſpace of halfe an houre; and then powre it out upon cold water, and let all the Fat that ſwims at top, bee gathered up with a ſpoone, and whatſoever
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:5454:5"/> 
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:5454:5"/> 
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:5454:6"/> ſinkes to the bottome, let it be caſt away.</p>
            <p>Then take two<note n="*" place="margin">A meaſure conteyning <hi>18.</hi> Ounces.</note> 
               <hi>Sextarios</hi> of <hi>Earth-wormes,</hi> waſh'd eyther in Wine or in Water, partch them in ſome Bakers oven, in a cover'd pot, yet take heed they burne not; and then let them bee bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to powder.</p>
            <p>
               <list>
                  <item>Take of this powder, — </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The dryed braines of a wilde Boare,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sweet red Saunders,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mummy,</hi> and</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Blood-ſtone,</hi> of each one Ounce:</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Then take the <hi>Moſſe of the scull of a Man,</hi> kill'd by ſome violent death, ſcraped off in the increaſe of the Moone ſhee being in a good houſe, as of <hi>Venus,</hi> if it may be, not of <hi>Mars</hi> or <hi>Saturne,</hi> in quantity about the weight of two Filberds: and of theſe broken mixt together with the Fat, let the Oyntment bee made according to Art, and kept ſafely in a cloſe Glaſſe or gally-pot for your uſe.</p>
            <p>If perchance in time this Oyntment ſhould wax dry; it may bee made ſupple and moyſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine with the foreſaid Fat, or <hi>Virgin-honey.</hi> Let this oyntment bee made the Sunne being in <hi>Libra.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Concerning the <hi>Vſe</hi> and <hi>Efficacie</hi> thereof, hee writeth thus. This <hi>Cure</hi> is done by the magne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique attractive power of this <hi>Salve,</hi> cauſed by the Starres, which by the mediation of the ayre, is carried and adjoyned to the Wound, that ſo the Spirituall operation thereof may bee effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:5454:6"/>
            <p>It is cauſed I ſay, by a Starry and Elementary conjunction. For as the heate of the Sunne doth joyne it ſelf with the Earth, ſo doth the<note n="*" place="margin">Perficar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome</hi> with the Wound; the Sunne departing the heate departs, ſo here likewiſe.</p>
            <p>There bee then Three things, which by this Oyntment doe worke this wonderfull effect. Firſt, Sympathy of Nature. Second, the influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the Celeſtiall bodies, perfecting its ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration by the Elements. Third, a <hi>Balſome</hi> which hath a power of healing, and is naturally given to every man.</p>
            <p>By this Oyntment are all wounds healed, by whatſoever, weapon, blow, or throw ſoever, they are made, or unto what Sex ſoever they are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted, (yet ſo, that neither one of the Nerves, or Arteries, or one of the principall Members bee hurt) ſo that the Weapon may bee had though the Patient, be many miles from us. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is of a conglutinating, ſuppurating, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newing nature, it ſuffers not any hurtfull Symp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome to grow, if it be rightly applyed.</p>
            <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">The manner of applying it.</note> let the Weapon with which the man is wounded, be annointed every day once if neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity require, and the wound be great; otherwiſe every ſecond or third day, will ſerve. Let it bee kept in a cleane linnen cloath, in a warme place, not too hot leaſt there accrue any hurt to the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient: and beware that the Weapon fall not downe, nor the winde blow on it in a cold place, for it will force the patient to madneſſe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, before you annoynt the Wound,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:5454:7"/> conſider whether the wound be made by a thruſt or point-wiſe; which if it bee, then let the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon be annoynted above, (and not below,) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending downe, otherwiſe it will hurt the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, but if you cannot know, how deepe or in what manner the Weapon went into the fleſh, you may annoynt it all, otherwiſe it ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth to annoynt the very place, with which the hurt was made.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, it is needleſſe to ſow up the wound as <hi>Barber-Surgions</hi> doe; but onely to binde it up every day with a cleane cloath, dipp'd in the V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine of the Patient.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, that day wherein any one doth annoynt the Weapon, let him abſtaine from Venery.</p>
            <p>Sixtly, before the annoynting of the Weapon, let the blood of the wounded perſon be ſpeedily ſtanched.</p>
            <p>Seaventhly, in Fracturies or breaking of bones, you may adde ſome of the powder of great <hi>Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wort,</hi> or the rootes of black <hi>Hellebore,</hi> to the oynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>Having the Weapon with the which any one hath bin hurt, and deſireth to know, whether the Patient will live or dye, you ſhall thus try it: If you ſprinkle powder of red <hi>Saunders,</hi> and <hi>Blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone,</hi> upon the Weapon, warmed over a few coales, ſo as one may well hold his hand upon it, if it ſweat drops of Blood the patient ſhall dye; if not, he ſhall eſcape.</p>
            <p>But if you would know, whether your Patient
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:5454:7"/> bee temperate in his drink or other neceſſaries; it is known if there appeare ſpots of bloud in the <hi>weapon:</hi> if there be none, hee carryeth himſelfe well.</p>
            <p>And note alſo; firſt, if you get not the weapon or ſword, yet any cut or violent hurt of the fleſh out of which iſſueth bloud, may be cured by this Oyntment; if that a little Sallow ſticke, dipp'd in the bloody cut; the bloud ſticking on it bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing dryed (not at the heate of the Sunne or fire, but of it ſelfe) be put into the fore-ſayd Oynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, kept in a cloſe boxe or glaſſe, and there left in it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, if it be a great deepe wound, it may be cleanſed every morning and bound up with a freſh cloth, without any other uſe of extrenuous Oyles, Ointments, or any ſuch like; and ſo this wound is cured of it ſelfe, howſoever inflicted; a little ſticke once dipp'd into the bloody wound or cut, and put in the Ointment in the Box, avai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth to a full cure.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, but ſo often as any new wound is to be cured; it requires alſo a new ſticke.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, but if the wound will not bleed, it muſt bee ſo long ſcarified with the little ſticke till it bleed.</p>
            <p>So alſo in curing the Tooth-ach, the Tooth that aketh is to be ſcarified with a pen-knife till it bleed, and then annoint the pen-knife, with this Oyntment, after the blood is dryed into it, and the paine will preſently ceaſe. If a Horſe be pric<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked in the foot with a nayle, draw out the nayle
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:5454:8"/> and annoint it, and the horſe foot will bee forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with cured without ſuppuration.</p>
            <p>After the ſame manner, may any creature that hath fleſh and bones be cured.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Oſwaldus Gabelchover in Practic. Germanic.</hi> deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribeth it thus:</p>
            <p>Take <hi>Bores greaſe,</hi> and <hi>Beares greaſe,</hi> of each a pound, they muſt be diſſolved and have red Wine powred into them;</p>
            <p>Then he addeth,
<list>
                  <item>powder of <hi>Blood ſtones,</hi> one ounce,</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Red ſaunders,</hi> ſixe drammes,</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Prepared Wormes,</hi> two drams.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Moſſe of a dead mans ſcull,</hi> as <hi>much as can bee had;</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>So he mixeth it, that it may make an oyntment: concerning the uſe, it is even the ſame that <hi>Crol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius</hi> hath.</p>
            <p>Others have this deſcription;</p>
            <p>Take the <hi>Lard of a wilde Bore,</hi> diſſolved at the fire, and powred upon water, as much as ſhall ſuffice,
<list>
                  <item>Powder of prepared <hi>Earth-wormes,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Blood ſtone,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Red ſanders,</hi> and</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Moſſe of a dead mans ſcull,</hi> as much as ſhall ſuffice. Mixe it at the fire.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iohannes Wittichius</hi> omitteth the <hi>Moſſe</hi> and thinketh it mattereth but little whether it be uſed or not. Neither addes he <hi>Mummy,</hi> nor <hi>Fat,</hi> nor <hi>Blood;</hi> which thing alſo others doe. And I my ſelfe knew one who profeſſed this Cure, who
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:5454:8"/> made this Oyntment as oft as he pleaſed, onely with the <hi>fat</hi> of a tame common <hi>Boare,</hi> and ſome few other things, without eyther <hi>Moſſe,</hi> or any thing at all, had out of the body of man.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iacobus Colerus</hi> that <hi>Polyprag non,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Colerus</hi> his deſcription.</note> 
               <hi>lib.</hi> 18. <hi>Oe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conomiae. cap.</hi> 154. giveth this deſcription.</p>
            <p>Take
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Wilde Boares</hi> and <hi>Beares greaſe,</hi> of each halfe a pound.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Tame Boares</hi> and <hi>Beares greaſe,</hi> of each halfe a pound.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Moſſe of a mans ſcull,</hi> an handfull.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Earth-wormes Menſ</hi> 5/4.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Blood-ſtone</hi> two ounces.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Red ſaunders,</hi> and</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Great Comfry roots,</hi> of each iij. ounces.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Mingle them with wine, &amp; make an oyntment.</p>
            <p>Of the time of making this Oyntment they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree not, <hi>Crollius</hi> will have it made the <hi>Sunne</hi> being in <hi>Libra;</hi> others confine the time in more narrow limits, onely to the 10. or 11. of <hi>Septem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.</hi> Others at any time.</p>
            <p>The uſe of this Oyntment hath beene before largely deſcrib'd by <hi>Crollius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The manner of uſing it.</note> ſo that I thinke it needleſſe to repeate it. The maine point is, that the wound it ſelfe is not to bee annoynted with this oyntment, but the weapon or inſtrument whatſoever it be, with which the wound was made; or if that cannot be had, another weapon or peece of wood; but eſpecially Sallow, or any other thing dipp'd or ſmear'd in the blood of the wounded perſon.</p>
            <p>Neyther think they it availes, whether the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient be preſent, or many miles abſent; Neyther
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:5454:9"/> take they any care of the wounded perſon; but of annointing the weapon: yet ſome, order that the wound be every day waſhed, and cleanſed with <hi>white Wine</hi> or <hi>Vrine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But leſt any man ſhould doubt of the effect of this oyntment, Firſt of all they produce experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: and <hi>Rudolphus Goclenius Iunior,</hi> writeth that he is able to nominate <hi>Emperors, Kings, Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Earles, Nobles</hi> whoſe authority and truth is not to be doubted of, which give teſtimony of the efficacie of this Oyntment.</p>
            <p>Moreover the Patrons of this Oyntment doubt not, but naturall cauſes may be given of this action; and <hi>Crollius</hi> calls them ignorant fooles that doubt of its efficacie, or referre the cure to Sorcery. And to make it appeare that the cure may be done by a naturall way, they prove at large, that firſt there are actions which no corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall touch interceding, are done by an hidden Sympathy or Magnetiſme as they call it. And ſo the Loadſtone draweth Iron, although it touch it not with its body, and maketh it move toward the Pole: the Starres alſo worke upon inferiour things, which they touch not bodily. The <hi>Cramp-fiſh</hi> affects his hand that toucheth it only with his <hi>Iavelin.</hi> There be ſome that cannot en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure to be where a <hi>Cat</hi> is, though ſhe bee lock'd up in a Cheſt that they ſee her not; and unleſſe the Cat be removed, or they goe out of the place they fall into a ſwoone. Dogs <hi>know</hi> the foot-ſteps of their Maſters, and of wilde Beaſts too, and follow them by their track. The ſhade
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:5454:9"/> of the <hi>Ewe-tree</hi> is hurtfull to many. And very many ſuch things which are obſerved in nature, they heape up as examples, of hidden actions, which becauſe they are moſt evident in the Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net or Loadſtone, are called Magneticall actions in generall.</p>
            <p>Another thing which they preſuppoſe is that there is a ſpirit of the world, diffuſed over the whole Vniverſe, which is the conveyer or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyance of all occult vertues and actions; and conjoyneth all the parts of the World, and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecteth a wonderfull harmonie between them.</p>
            <p>But thirdly, concerning the vertues of this <hi>Weapon-ſalve</hi> it ſelf, they determine a double o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration to bee in it; one in the <hi>Oyntment</hi> it ſelf, that is, the healing and cloſing up of the wounds: the other which is in the <hi>Weapon</hi> annointed, and carryeth that vertue to the wound. They de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the former operation, from thoſe many things of which this <hi>Salve</hi> is compoſed, from the influence of the Starres, and a Syderiall and Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary conjunction: and therefore as hath been ſayd, ſome make this Oyntment at a certain time of the yeare, and in a certaine poſition of the Starres.</p>
            <p>The other operation they deduce from the <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall Balſam;</hi> which with the bloud ſticketh faſt to the weapon or inſtrument, thruſt into the wound and ſtained with the blood of the woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded perſon. For this <hi>Balſam</hi> by reaſon of a ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathy it hath with the part wounded, doth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:5454:10"/> that vertue of the Salve to the wound, the ſpirit of the world intervening and mediating betweene them.</p>
            <p>And of this thing they bring other Examples alſo; the Zenith (as they call it,) or the firſt menſtruous blood of young Maides, being caſt into the fire, as they report, is very offenſive unto the Virgin from whom it flowed. The Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundines or after births, if they bee ill hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, are very dangerous to the Women, from whom they come; although neyther in this doe they declare themſelves plainly enough: For <hi>Crollius</hi> writeth, that this Cure is perfected, by the attractive magneticall operation of this <hi>Salve;</hi> which by the mediation of the <hi>Ayre</hi> is brought, and conjoyned to the <hi>Wound.</hi> And pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently after hee ſayth, there be three things which by this Medicament, doe cauſe ſo wonderfull an effect; Firſt, <hi>Naturall Sympathy.</hi> Second, <hi>The in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence of Celeſtiall bodyes, perfecting their operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons by the Elements.</hi> Third, <hi>A Balſome which hath a healing vertue, and is in every man by nature.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Reaſons a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Defenders of Weapon-Salve.</note>But to give our owne opinion of this Oynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; <hi>Firſt,</hi> this maketh it to bee ſuſpected, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe one manner of compoſing it, is not agreed on: but there are many, and in ſome thoſe things are omitted from which others deduce, all the vertue of this <hi>Salve;</hi> as appeares plainly out of the fore-named Deſcriptions.</p>
            <p>Thus, <hi>Wittichius</hi> omits <hi>Moſſe, Fat,</hi> and <hi>Blood,</hi> which others account the foundation and chiefe
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:5454:10"/> part of this <hi>Salve,</hi> and yet all of them promiſe the ſame effect, and every one extols his owne oyntment for Curing all kindes of hurts done, with what kinde of <hi>Weapon</hi> ſoever, whether Stab or Cut with a blow or a fall: although <hi>Gocleni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> and <hi>Crollius</hi> except thoſe Wounds, which are in the <hi>Nerves, arteries,</hi> or principall <hi>members,</hi> as the <hi>Heart</hi> and <hi>Braine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereas others object againſt the compoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this <hi>Salve,</hi> that the Authors of this Oynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment doe uſe, the <hi>Moſſe</hi> of a man hang'd, <hi>Mum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,</hi> warme <hi>Blood,</hi> and <hi>Fat</hi> of men, and doe think the whole power and efficacie of this thing to be in <hi>Mans fat</hi> and <hi>blood;</hi> and therefore, think it ſuperſtitious: I aſſent not to them, ſince it is very well knowne, that the <hi>Fat</hi> and <hi>ſculls</hi> of men, and <hi>Mummy,</hi> and <hi>Moſſe,</hi> are uſed by other Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians, to cure Diſeaſes without ſuperſtition.</p>
            <p>Yet this I adviſe, that foraſmuch as Witches and Wizards, as appeares, out of <hi>Apuleius Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamorph. lib.</hi> 2, <hi>&amp;</hi> 3. And <hi>Nicolas Remigius, lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 16. <hi>&amp; Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. <hi>De demonolatria;</hi> and out of others which have writ concerning <hi>Witches,</hi> That they are wont to uſe the <hi>Blood</hi> and <hi>Fleſh</hi> of a Man, and other parts of mans body, for their <hi>Sorceries,</hi> that every one who will uſe ſuch things ſhould take heed, that hee doe not ſuperſtitiouſly uſe a Salve, for producing a naturall effect; and ſo gratifie the Divell, and unawares ſerve him, who is the Enemy both of mans Body and ſoule: which may bee done, if wee uſe ſuch things to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:5454:11"/> thoſe effects, which are not in the Naturall pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the things.</p>
            <p>And therefore if they finde event, it is rather to bee imputed and aſcribed to the Divell, lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſnares for men by ſuch ſuperſtitious meanes, than to the thing it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Now concerning the effect of this <hi>Salve, Guilielmus Fabritius, Obſervat.</hi> 25. <hi>Cent.</hi> 3. ſayth, That it doth not alwayes anſwer their expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: and that it may bee, that many have beene healed, that have uſed this <hi>Salve,</hi> and ſo many great men can teſtifie; yet they can teſtifie no more then this, that one was wounded; and that this <hi>Weapon-Salve</hi> was applyed for the Cure, and that hee grew well againe: but they cannot teſtifie, whether hee recovered by the efficacy of this <hi>Salve.</hi> For many things may oftentimes bee conjoyned with the effect, which are not the cauſe of it; ſo that as it followeth not: While this man was walking it Lightened, therefore his walking is the cauſe of the Lightening: ſo it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes not; This wounded man, is healed, and hath uſed the <hi>Weapon-Salve,</hi> therefore the <hi>Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon-Salve</hi> is the cauſe of his healing; Vnleſſe it may appeare that this effect, hath neceſſarily fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed from this <hi>Weapon-Salve.</hi> Nor is the<note n="*" place="margin">When that is taken to be the Cauſe, which is not the Cauſe.</note> 
               <hi>fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacie of the Cauſe,</hi> more frequent any where then in <hi>Phyſicke;</hi> where oft-times the Cure of a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe is attributed to a <hi>Medicine,</hi> when it proceeds not from it; but from <hi>nature,</hi> or ſome other <hi>ſalve,</hi> eyther uſed before, or together with it.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:5454:11"/>
            <p>And indeed, the reaſon of <hi>Phyſique</hi> is farre different, from that of other <hi>Arts.</hi> For in other Arts the effect, altogether wholly dependeth up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Artificer;</hi> and if any thing bee done ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther well or ill by him, (unleſſe perhaps, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the unfitneſſe of the matter and ſubject, (for <hi>Ex quolibet ligno non fit mercurius,</hi>) or by reaſon of the Inſtrument ſome fault may hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen) all is to bee imputed and aſcribed, to the <hi>Artificer</hi> ſeeing, as I have ſhewed (<hi>Inſtit. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 1.) the ſubjects of other Arts worke nothing, but onely ſubmit themſelves to be wrought on: but the ſubject of <hi>Phyſique</hi> hath a certaine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred power, whereby aſſiſted by the <hi>Phyſitians</hi> help, it doth for the moſt part, of its owne ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord tend to health, whence it is that HIP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>POCRATES ſayth, 6. <hi>Epid. Com.</hi> 5. <hi>Text.</hi> 1. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Natures are the Phyſitians of diſeaſes.</p>
            <p>The point therefore is this, that here the ſtate of the controverſie is not, whether in the <hi>Cure</hi> of the wounded perſon now recovered, the <hi>Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon-Salve</hi> was applyed, but whether the <hi>Weapon-Salve</hi> was the cauſe of the healing: of which now wee are to make enquirie.</p>
            <p>But ſeeing (as it is ſayd before) <hi>Nature</hi> may be the <hi>cauſe</hi> of cloſing up a <hi>wound,</hi> and not the vertue of any <hi>Medicine</hi> by what name ſoever it be called: yea oftentimes wounds are cured with <hi>Lard</hi> or ſome other ſmall thing layd to, without the help
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:5454:12"/> of a <hi>Phyſitian</hi> or any other <hi>Medicaments.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the cure which is thought to be done by the <hi>Weapon ſalve,</hi> the cloſing of the wound is to be attributed onely to <hi>Nature;</hi> as the next and principall cauſe. Which ſince it is ſo; and it can by no meanes bee denyed; now the <hi>Queſtion</hi> is, whether in that cure the healing of the <hi>wound,</hi> be aſcribed to <hi>Nature</hi> onely, or whether ſome effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacie of this <hi>Weapon ſalve</hi> doth concurre together with it. The former ſeemeth to me to bee the more probable, becauſe it is certaine, as was ſaid even now, that <hi>wounds</hi> are very often healed by <hi>Nature,</hi> without the helpe of any <hi>Medicament.</hi> This, the inward <hi>wounds,</hi> to which no <hi>Medica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> can bee applyed, doe teſtifie: and hither tendeth all that diſcourſe of <hi>Caeſar Magatus</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the courſe of curing wounds, of which is ſpoken in the precedent Chapter, that the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe be committed to <hi>Nature,</hi> the heate and temper of the part, (which is an inſtrument) be kept ſound, and not be troubled with <hi>Medica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> where there is no neceſſity: and ſometime ſuch dangerous wounds, are healed chiefly, by the helpe of <hi>Nature,</hi> and by none at all, or elſe but ſlender <hi>Medicaments</hi> applyed; ſo that it may ſeeme to be aſcribed, rather to a <hi>Miracle</hi> then <hi>medicaments.</hi> The obſervations and examples whereof are every where well knowne; Neither are the Patrons of this <hi>Oyntment</hi> ſo bold as to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend its power to all wounds, ſeeing (as was ſaid) <hi>Crollius</hi> and <hi>Groclenius</hi> except the wounds
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:5454:12"/> of the <hi>Principall members,</hi> and alſo of the <hi>Nerves</hi> and <hi>Arteries;</hi> and no man was ever yet found, who durſt uſe this <hi>Oyntment</hi> about ſuch as have beene wounded by <hi>Gun ſhot.</hi> And who is there, that dareth deny, that other ſmaller wounds may be healed onely by <hi>Nature?</hi> yet if any thing fall out in the cure by the <hi>Weapon ſalve,</hi> which may exceed the <hi>power of Nature,</hi> take heed it bee not done by the helpe of the <hi>Divell,</hi> drawne thereto by ſome implicite or explicite compact.</p>
            <p>Seeing then <hi>Nature</hi> onely and immediately cloſeth up <hi>Wounds,</hi> &amp; <hi>Salves</hi> (as hath been ſhewed before) ſerve for no other uſe, then to conſerve native heat, and naturall temper of the part, or to remove thoſe impediments, which hinder nature in its worke; we are now to conſider, whether this <hi>Weapon ſalve</hi> can doe thoſe things.</p>
            <p>Where the firſt difficulty is this; whether or no, there is any <hi>ſalve</hi> at all, that can doe any good not being <hi>annointed</hi> on the <hi>wound it ſelf,</hi> but on the <hi>weapon</hi> or ſome other thing ſtained with the <hi>blood</hi> out of the wound: chiefly, if the <hi>wounded perſon</hi> be abſent, and be diſtant from the weapon that is annointed, the ſpace of ſome certaine miles. To prove it they uſe two reaſons, as is ſaid before; The firſt is, that there is ſome actions, from the <hi>occult</hi> qualities called <hi>Magneticall</hi> which worke at a diſtance; and againe, that the <hi>power</hi> of this <hi>Oyntment</hi> is conveyed to the <hi>wound,</hi> by the <hi>Spirit</hi> of the world; as the <hi>Sympathy</hi> and <hi>Antipathy</hi> of many things.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:5454:13"/>
            <p>But neyther Argument proveth the thing they ſhould. For firſt of all, though wee grant that there are ſuch <hi>actions,</hi> which mutually do worke upon and ſuffer one from another, though they bee not alwayes united by corporall contact. Notwithſtanding, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>her this happen in the <hi>Weapon ſalve;</hi> or whether, any vertue or force be brought to the wound, from the <hi>annointed weapon</hi> through a great diſtance of place; that is not yet proved. Neyther doth it follow, that becauſe there are <hi>miraculous actions</hi> of other things, therefore this <hi>Weapon ſalve</hi> ſhould have ſuch a vertue. And that this is not ſo, he who ſhall enquire into other the like actions of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture;</hi> which are done at a diſtance, ſhall eaſily perceive.</p>
            <p>Seeing that <hi>Operation</hi> doth follow the beeing of a thing; It is neceſſary, there muſt bee a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine <hi>Conjunction,</hi> and mutuall <hi>Contact</hi> betweene the <hi>Agent</hi> and the <hi>Patient:</hi> And againe, ſeeing that things betweene which there is action, touch not one another with their bodies; it is neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry they ſhould touch ſome other way; and that may be two wayes: For eyther the thing which is ſayd to work at diſtance, ſends out ſomewhat from its body and ſubſtance, which the <hi>Ancients</hi> call <hi>effluvium, ſeu</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, an <hi>Over-flowing,</hi> or <hi>Flux:</hi> the <hi>Phyſitians</hi> where they ſpeake of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagion,</hi> call it <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, (See our <hi>Lib.</hi> 4. <hi>de Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bribus, cap.</hi> 4. <hi>&amp; Inſtitut. Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Part.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 12.)
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:5454:13"/> To wit, where the ſmalleſt parts or atomes flow out of the bodie, and the ayre or ſome other bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy mediating, are transferr'd to another body; and doe worke upon it by the vertue which they have common with the intire body from which they flow. But ſuch like little bodies, and effluxes have no regular motion, but are diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly moved hither and thither, according to the motion of the ayre, and by any breath are vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly diſperſed, as wee may ſee in the ſmoake of a <hi>Candle,</hi> and other lighted things being extingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed and put out.</p>
            <p>Other bodies which are ſaid to work at a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, ſend not forth any thing of their owne proper body, which is carried to another body; but only a <hi>Species</hi> or ſemblance: after this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner bodies farre diſtant, are affected or wrought by the <hi>Species ſenſibiles,</hi> as by <hi>Light,</hi> by <hi>Sound,</hi> by <hi>Smell:</hi> and it is probable that there are more ſuch ſpecies or reſemblances, then are apprehended by our ſenſes: and this commonly is ſayd to bee done by a virtuall contact. Yet this vertue doth alwayes preſuppoſe a ſubject out of which it flowes; ſo the flame being out, the illumina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or enlightening of the things about it cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth. Beſides, a fit ſubject is required by which it may bee propagated, which if it bee not, the action ceaſeth. So if a darke body be interpoſed between the <hi>light</hi> and our <hi>ſight,</hi> the illumination ceaſeth. Thirdly, this vertue is diffus'd round about a certaine diſtance: <hi>Philoſophers</hi> call it, <hi>the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:5454:14"/> Spheare of Activitie;</hi> which in ſome things is greater, in ſome things leſſe.</p>
            <p>It is greateſt in things that ſend out <hi>Light;</hi> it is leaſt in thoſe that make <hi>Sounds:</hi> yet by how much the greater the light body is, by ſo much the greater is its <hi>Spheare of activitie:</hi> Hence it is, that <hi>Starres</hi> doe diſperſe light from them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in the greateſt diſtance and fartheſt off, of all other bodies.</p>
            <p>Now therefore the queſtion is, becauſe it is certaine, that the <hi>Weapon-Salve</hi> with which the <hi>Weapon</hi> is annoynted is corporally abſent from the wounded perſon, whether there bee any contact by eyther of theſe wayes, a third way can not bee named. Nor can it bee done by any accident, or quality; For an accident, paſſeth not out of one <hi>Subiect</hi> into another; neither can it diffuſe it ſelfe into another and diſtant body. I ſay it cannot bee done by eyther of theſe wayes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Weapon-ſalve wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth not by any Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall effluxe.</note>For firſt of all, whereas corporall Fluxes can have no certaine motion, but are inordinately carried hither and thither, according to the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Ayre,</hi> how ſhall they directly come to the <hi>wounded</hi> perſon? Neither availes it, that any one ſhould flee for anſwere to the <hi>ſimilitude</hi> of their ſubſtance. For although ſuch little bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies doe in the end apply themſelves to that which is of their owne kinde, as wee may ſee in the <hi>Thunder</hi> and <hi>Lightening:</hi> yet notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, while they doe firſt breake out from their body, they doe inordinately wander about here
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:5454:14"/> and there. Much leſſe is it availeable to flee to the <hi>Spirit of the world;</hi> by which theſe little bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, may be conveyed from the annointed <hi>Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon,</hi> to the wounds.</p>
            <p>For thoſe things concerning the <hi>Spirit of the World;</hi> are ſayd, but are not proved; yea rather are oppoſed, with ſufficient ſtrong <hi>Arguments.</hi> Moreover ſeeing this <hi>Cure</hi> extends it ſelte farre off, and as they will have it, for ſome number of miles; if it ſhould bee done by the effuſion of thoſe ſmall bodyes; whereas but a very little of the <hi>Oyntment</hi> and leſſe of the naturall <hi>Balſam,</hi> doth adhere to the <hi>Weapon;</hi> that <hi>Oyntment</hi> with the <hi>Balſam</hi> would eaſily turne into <hi>Ayre</hi> and vaniſh away: and ſo the originall of the <hi>Cure</hi> being taken away, the cure of it ſelfe ſhould ceaſe.</p>
            <p>But if they ſay that this <hi>Action</hi> is done by <hi>Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies,</hi> or a <hi>magnetique action,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Weapon Salve wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth not by Species.</note> they muſt firſt prove that there are ſuch <hi>ſpecies</hi> in the <hi>Oyntment.</hi> (For <hi>Nature</hi> hath given the power of ſending forth <hi>ſpecies</hi> or <hi>ſemblances</hi> of this kinde, to ſome cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine things <hi>ſimple</hi> and <hi>naturall,</hi> not compoſed by <hi>Art,</hi>) and then they muſt ſhew us what the <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> of theſe things is, and what the Spheare is of their activity. For neither is it credible, that the vertue of this <hi>Oyntment</hi> ſhould extend it ſelfe <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bicularly,</hi> or every way round about for the ſpace of 12. miles.</p>
            <p>As concerning the <hi>Loadſtone,</hi> from whence thoſe actions uſe to be call'd <hi>Magneticall,</hi> the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:5454:15"/> 
               <hi>Loadſtone</hi> indeed attracteth the <hi>Iron</hi> which is a little way diſtant from it; but that which is very farre off, and beyond the <hi>Spheare</hi> of its <hi>activity,</hi> it attracts not; which alſo is knowne to be done, in other <hi>occult</hi> and <hi>magneticall</hi> actions of the ſame kinde. The <hi>Loadſtone</hi> alſo and other things of this ſort, put forth their vertue by a right line, which notwithſtanding is not extended <hi>in infini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi> or without limits; and oftentimes alſo is hindered by the <hi>interpoſition</hi> of other things. So the Sun-beames are excluded by the <hi>interpoſition</hi> of a darke body. Who therefore can beleeve, that out of ſo little <hi>Oyntment,</hi> and as little <hi>Blood,</hi> ſo many little bodies or <hi>Species</hi> can breake tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the <hi>Cheſt</hi> in which the <hi>Weapon</hi> annoynted is ſhut up, to bee carryed a great diſtance even the ſpace of twelve miles, to penetrate <hi>Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines</hi> and <hi>Walls,</hi> and directly to come to the <hi>wounded</hi> perſon, ſhut up in his Chamber, and goe through a great many Rollers in which the <hi>wound</hi> is wrapped, and inſinuate it ſelfe into the <hi>wound?</hi> The <hi>Loadſtone</hi> is put to the <hi>Iron</hi> it ſelf; but this <hi>Oyntment</hi> is not applyed to the <hi>Wound</hi> but to the <hi>Weapon.</hi> The <hi>Loadſtone</hi> applyed to the <hi>Iron,</hi> attracts it after one manner, but in the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying of this <hi>Oyntment</hi> aright, how many ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious wayes of annointing there are uſed; hath bin already declared. And in other reſpects too there is a great difference betweene, the <hi>Loadſtone</hi> and the <hi>Weapon ſalve:</hi> for the <hi>Load<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone</hi> is a naturall <hi>Bodie,</hi> and hath its naturall <hi>ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects,</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:5454:15"/> which it alwayes produceth after the ſame manner; the <hi>Weapon ſalve</hi> is a thing by divers men compounded of different ingredients, and made after a different manner, as hath been ſayd before.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Oyntment</hi> alſo by theſe mens opinions, is to produce divers effects, and to performe all things that are neceſſary to the healing of a wound: to keepe the <hi>wound</hi> free from paine, and if it be not kept orderly, or be ſoyled, to cauſe paine. For if it ought to performe that in the cure of wounds, which otherwayes is the <hi>worke of nature,</hi> it is neceſſary that it muſt doe many things: namely, it muſt digeſt that which is to be digeſted, it muſt expell corruption and <hi>excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> and <hi>beget fleſh;</hi> and muſt doe both the <hi>offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of a Phyſitian</hi> and <hi>Salve</hi> too, which are diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent. For neyther are the bodies wounded al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes of the ſame diſpoſition, but ſome are ſound, others are full of <hi>corruption,</hi> and abound with <hi>vitious humours;</hi> the parts are divers, as <hi>Fleſh, Nerves, Membranes,</hi> which require <hi>ſalves</hi> of divers ſorts, the efficacie of all which, this <hi>Weapon ſalve</hi> muſt containe; And if one at the ſame time ſhould receive divers <hi>wounds</hi> in divers places, which oft times falls out from divers <hi>weapons,</hi> is it enough to annoint one weapon for all? And is the efficacy thereof carryed to all the other wounds? Or muſt every particular <hi>weapon</hi> be annointed? And whether will every particular <hi>Oyntment</hi> or <hi>Salve</hi> doe its proper
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:5454:16"/> office, ſo that this goeth directly to this <hi>wound,</hi> that was made by this <hi>weapon,</hi> and that to that <hi>wound</hi> which was done by another <hi>weapon?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A reaſon alſo ſhould be given, why the <hi>Oynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> ſhould not worke the ſame <hi>effect</hi> being in the box, which it will doe, being annointed on the <hi>weapon.</hi> Neyther can it be, as they ſay, that the <hi>force</hi> of this <hi>Oyntment</hi> ſhould bee carryed to the wound by the helpe of the <hi>Balſome,</hi> which is in the blood. For if that blood <hi>it ſelfe</hi> ſhould be reduced into <hi>Atomes,</hi> it were not able to reach through ſuch a great diſtance. Neyther yet they proved that the blood can ſend forth any ſuch <hi>ſpecies;</hi> and if by the benefit of the blood the power of this <hi>Salve,</hi> is carryed to the wound, why then ſhould it not carry to the wound the <hi>efficacy</hi> of other things, on which the blood of the wounded is divers times ſhed, which we ſee is not done.</p>
            <p>As for thoſe things, which in particular they alledge of the <hi>Secundines,</hi> and firſt <hi>menſtruous blood of Maides,</hi> and determine that if any abuſe bee done to them, the <hi>women</hi> alſo ſuffer: thoſe things are to be aſcribed to the <hi>Superſtitions of women.</hi> For if in mankinde the <hi>Secundines of women,</hi> being caſt into ſome ſordid place, doe annoy the party; why is it not ſo in <hi>Brutes,</hi> when their <hi>Secundines</hi> are caſt into the mire and rot? Beſides, in what place ſoever theſe <hi>Secundines</hi> be buried, yet they doe putrifie notwithſtanding. Why doe not the <hi>exuberant lumps of fleſh</hi> which women burne,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:5454:16"/> doe hurt to the women? Why doth the firſt <hi>menſtruous bloud</hi> being burnt annoy the <hi>Virgin,</hi> and not other that commeth after.</p>
            <p>Therefore theſe things being ſo, wee need not ſeriouſly to diſpute what power is in this <hi>Oynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> for the <hi>cure of a wound:</hi> ſeeing hitherto, we have ſufficiently proved, that none commeth from the <hi>Oyntment</hi> to the <hi>wound:</hi> and if this have any power eyther of preſerving or cheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing the <hi>temper of nature,</hi> or <hi>heate of the part,</hi> (which they call <hi>Balſome</hi>) or drying <hi>up excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments:</hi> they might better apply it to the <hi>woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded part,</hi> then annoint it on the Weapon. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, if the power and ſtrength of this <hi>Oyntment</hi> conſiſt in the <hi>Fat</hi> or <hi>bloud of man,</hi> (as ſome would have it) why then doe many of them apply it to the wounds of ſome Beaſts, for example, of <hi>Horſes?</hi> For how great a difference is there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene a <hi>Man</hi> and a <hi>Horſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now whereas <hi>Crollius</hi> and ſome others (that I omit not their conceit) draw the power of this <hi>Oyntment</hi> from the Heavens, and therefore would have it made in ſome certaine <hi>Poſition</hi> thereof; neyther doth this further their cauſe. For they have not yet proved, that there is any power of healing eyther in the <hi>Heaven</hi> or in the <hi>Starres,</hi> or if there were, that they ſo communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate it to this <hi>Ointment,</hi> that it beeing as it were ſhut up and kept cloſe, may bee carried up and downe, and when they pleaſe bee produced into uſe.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:5454:17"/>
            <p>Moreover for the <hi>manner of uſing</hi> this <hi>Oynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> it hath no ground, neyther is it without <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition.</hi> For firſt, when they make the whole <hi>cauſe of the Cure</hi> to bee, that the power of this <hi>Oyntment</hi> is convayed to the <hi>wound</hi> by reaſon of that <hi>naturall Balſome</hi> which is in the blood, why then doe they annoint that <hi>weapon</hi> with which a man was <hi>wounded,</hi> or another weapon or a piece of wood beſmeared with the bloud of the <hi>wound;</hi> and doe not annoint the ſhirt, or ſome other gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the affected perſon, or a ſtone or any thing elſe upon which the bloud is powred, if there be not ſome implicite compact contrac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the <hi>Divell?</hi> And then if the <hi>wound</hi> bee made by a Stab or <hi>point-wiſe</hi> they annoint the weapon on the point towards the Hilt; and if with a blow from the edge, towards the back, and if it may be ſeene how farre the ſword hath <hi>penetrated</hi> the wound, then they annoynt it ſo farre as it hath <hi>penetrated;</hi> if not, they annoint it all: which things are ſuperſtitious, whereof no reaſon can be given.</p>
            <p>If the power of this <hi>Oyntment</hi> bee <hi>Naturall,</hi> what effect doth that manner of annoynting produce? whether doth it adde any new power or quality? If the vertue be naturall, there needs no <hi>Ceremonies;</hi> as appeareth in all naturall things. The <hi>Loadſtone</hi> draweth <hi>Iron,</hi> and the <hi>Iron</hi> touch'd with the <hi>Loadſtone</hi> maketh towards the <hi>Pole,</hi> without uſing any Ceremonies.</p>
            <p>Moreover ſome annoynt the Weapon once
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:5454:17"/> every day, ſome annoint it every other day, ſome every third day, ſome onely once: others leſt they ſhould faile in the annointing of it, doe for a perfect Cure bury the Weapon or a Sallow ſticke that is inſtead of it; in the <hi>Oyntment</hi> which is left in a Boxe, but they neglect the Weapon who wholly cover it or that which is inſtead of it in the <hi>Oyntment;</hi> Others when they have annointed the Weapon keepe it in ſome tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate place, others ſhut it up in a Cheſt; and all of them take care, that the Weapon be not in a place too hot or too cold, and that it bee not ſoyl'd with any durtineſſe: For if this happen, it hindreth the <hi>Cure,</hi> and brings great paine to the affected and wounded perſon: All which things are frivolous and ſuperſtitious; For ſeeing that it hath beene ſufficiently proved, that there is no action of this <hi>Weapon ſalve,</hi> on the <hi>wound,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing farre aſunder from the <hi>wound;</hi> neyther can it cauſe any <hi>Griefe.</hi> And therefore if it happen according to the deſire of him that uſeth the <hi>Medicine,</hi> it is done by the helpe of the <hi>Divell.</hi> Doubtleſſe the bloud of wounded perſons, is not alwayes ſpilt in cleane places, but ſometimes in foule ones; it is <hi>frozen</hi> in <hi>Winter,</hi> &amp; the bloody Rags are waſh'd in warme water; <hi>Sticks</hi> ſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with the bloud are burned, and yet the <hi>wounded perſon</hi> feeles no hurt.</p>
            <p>Finally, they aſcribe very <hi>impoſsibilities</hi> to this <hi>Oyntment,</hi> and ſuch operations which in one na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall <hi>medicine</hi> cannot be found. For they affirme
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:5454:18"/> that all <hi>Wounds</hi> made with a <hi>ſtab,</hi> or with a <hi>blow,</hi> by a <hi>fall</hi> or by a <hi>throw,</hi> may bee cured by this <hi>Oyntment.</hi> But great is the diverſity of <hi>Wounds,</hi> according to their ſeverall circumſtances, and ſo not one onely <hi>Salve,</hi> but divers are requiſite to their <hi>Cure.</hi> A <hi>Wound</hi> made with a <hi>ſharpe-pointed weapon,</hi> is cured without the generation of much <hi>corruption.</hi> But in that which is bruiſed, whatſoever is bruiſed muſt needs turne to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption. There is great diverſity alſo in the parts; A wound in a <hi>fleſhy part,</hi> eſpecially in a ſound and <hi>well-temper'd</hi> man, is eaſily cured, but farre more difficult is it to cure a wound, given in the <hi>Braine, Nerves, Sinewes, Ligaments,</hi> eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially the great <hi>Ligaments,</hi> as thoſe of the <hi>Hams:</hi> They promiſe alſo to cure wounds without any <hi>Paine,</hi> which in every part to performe, is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible. Verily if a <hi>Nerve</hi> be prick'd, no man can performe that the <hi>Patient,</hi> ſhall not be pained. And therefore to conclude this buſineſſe, the cure of a wound which is aſcribed to the <hi>Weapon-ſalve,</hi> is for the moſt part the worke of meere <hi>Nature,</hi> which not onely cureth ſmall wounds, but very great ones; which appeares from this, that there are ſuch divers deſcriptions of this <hi>Weapon-ſalve;</hi> and that ſome inſtead of this <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded Weapon-ſalve,</hi> uſe onely <hi>Lard</hi> or <hi>Hogs-greaſe;</hi> and yet nevertheleſſe have cured wounds, which the fore-cited <hi>Iohan. Colerus in his Oeco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nom.</hi> in the place before cited, affirmeth hee hath ſeene. But if by the application of this <hi>Oynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:5454:18"/> any very great wound bee cured, ſo that it ſeeme to ſurpaſſe the ſtrength of <hi>Nature,</hi> this <hi>Cure</hi> is atchieved by the helpe or power of the <hi>Divell</hi> himſelfe, drawne thereto by ſome cloſe or open compact.</p>
            <p>Neither doth it take away the ſuſpicion here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of will ſome ſay: namely, that all the ſimples uſed in the compoſition of this <hi>Oyntment</hi> are meerely naturall, and that no <hi>Characters, Conjuratians</hi> or <hi>Charms,</hi> are uſed in the making or uſing thereof. For the <hi>Divell</hi> can conceale his <hi>compact,</hi> not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly under <hi>Characters</hi> and <hi>Conſecrations,</hi> and a ſet forme of words, but alſo under <hi>naturall cauſes:</hi> if at his command things <hi>naturall</hi> (which are uſed in the firſt and <hi>explicite Covenant,</hi> to the which <hi>cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant</hi> others implicitely which uſe the ſame things, may unawares interpoſe themſelves) are us'd to another uſe, then they were created of good: and ſo <hi>Magicall</hi> and diveliſh actions are co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, and ſhifted in under the vaile of <hi>Magnetique actions.</hi> It being granted then (which for the moſt part we affirme to be done by the benefit of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi>) that the wounded perſon is healed by this <hi>Oyntment;</hi> it is not impoſſible but credible, that the <hi>Divell</hi> may ſome way helpe the body that he may deſtroy the ſoule. Seeing he is mans greateſt enemy, and by every way that he can, is ready to hurt him; and therefore as much as in him lyes, he draweth man from God, our bountifull <hi>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour,</hi> and from meanes ordained by him, to things full of Superſtition.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
